Finding Aid for Hobart Taylor, Jr. Papers 1961-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hobart Taylor, Jr. Papers 1961-1981
Taylor, Hobart, 1920-1981.
(in 25 boxes)
23.1 linear feet
Attorney and businessman, associate counsel to President Lyndon Johnson, later director of the Export-Import Bank; correspondence, speeches, and oral history interviews; files relating to his work with Plans for Progress, a voluntary association of business and industry working to promote equal employment opportunities; his work on the President's Committee on Equal Employment Opportunities, the NAACP, the Commandant of the Marine Corps' Advisory Committee for Minority Affairs; topical files relating to Democratic politics in the 1960s, and his work with Johnson and Vice-President Hubert Humphrey; and photographs.
85542 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Taylor papers were received from Hobart Taylor, Jr. (donor 5443 ) in four accessions, beginning in 1973. The major body of material was received in December 1981.
The collection is open for research.
Hobart Taylor, Jr. was born on December 17, 1920 in Texarkana, Texas. He attended Houston public schools, received an A.B. from Prairie View State College (1939) and an A.M. in economics from Howard University (1941). He attended law school at the University of Michigan, where he was a student editor of the Michigan Law Review. In 1943 he received a J.D. from the University, and in 1944 he was admitted to the Michigan Bar.
Taylor was employed from 1944-1945 as a research assistant to the Chief Justice of the Michigan Supreme Court. He became a junior partner in the Detroit law firm of Bledsoe & Taylor (1945-1948) and then a senior member of the firm Taylor, Patrick, Bailer & Toe, also of Detroit (1958-1961).
From 1951-1961, he was an assistant prosecuting attorney in Wayne County, Michigan.
Taylor began work in the federal Government shortly after the inauguration of the Kennedy-Johnson Administration in January 1961. He became a special assistant to then Vice-President Lyndon Johnson and also served as Special Counsel to the President's Committee on Equal Employment Opportunities (PCEEO), which was formed in 1961 by President Kennedy to end hiring bias by government contractors and agencies. Having been given the authority to actually cancel contracts of non-complying firms or unions, this Committee proved more effective than its two Eisenhower predecessors-the Committee or Government Contracts and the Committee on Government Employment Policy.
In September, 1962, President Kennedy appointed Taylor Executive Vice Chairman of the President's Committee; he thus became the first non-white head of a Presidential committee staff. Taylor held this position until 1965 in addition to continuing his work as special counsel to the Committee.
While Executive Chairman, Taylor worked with Charles E. Spahr, then President and later Board Chairman of Standard Oil of Ohio, when Spahr was chairman of the Advisory Council to Plans for Progress, a voluntary cooperative association of major American corporations in support of equal employment opportunity. Taylor contributed to the Plans for Progress program by seeking to include employers in every field; by enlisting greater Participation of labor; by setting up special education programs at colleges and universities; by moving into Southern areas like Birmingham, Alabama; and by convincing the advertising industry to conduct a nationwide equal employment campaign. Taylor was also instrumental in bringing about non-discriminatory hiring practices by contractors at the federal space center in Huntsville, Alabama.
In April, 1964, President Johnson appointed Taylor Associate Counsel to the President. From this office at the White House, Taylor continued to direct the activities of the President's Committee while carrying out his responsibilities as Associate Counsel. Taylor resigned both positions when he became a Director of the Export-Import Bank in 1965, but at the request of Vice-President Hubert Humphrey, he continued to help direct the Plans for Progress program.
Taylor returned to private law practice in 1968 as a partner in the Washington, D.C. law firm of Dawson, Riddell, Taylor, Davis & Holroyd in which he remained until 1979. In 1980, he was named Counsel for Jones, Day, Reavis & Pogue, also of Washington, D.C.
Taylor's extensive business interests over the years included board of director memberships in such prestigious American corporations as Aetna Life Insurance Co., A & P, Standard Oil of Ohio, Westinghouse, National Urban Corporation, Eastern Air Lines, and the Burroughs Corporation.
Taylor was involved over the years in a number of civic and charitable activities. He was, for example, active in the affairs of the Democratic National Committee and helped to plan the Lyndon Johnson Inauguration (Jan., 1965). He was a leading figure in the NAACP and served for many years as a Trustee of the NAACP Special Contributions Fund. In 1979 he became a member of the National Board of the NAACP. He was a trustee of Dillard University, Howard University, and the Loomis Institute (Windsor, Connecticut).
Taylor's other charitable and civic activities include the following: Board member, A Better Chance, Inc. (1964-1972); Board member, National Merit Scholarship Corporation (1965-1973); official representative of President Johnson to the Fifth Anniversary Celebration of the Republic of the Ivory Coast in Africa (1966); Chairman, Commandant of the Marine Corps' Advisory Committee on Minority Affairs (1968-1974); Governor and member of the Executive Committee, American National Red Cross (1970-1978); member, Commission on Postal Service (1977-1978); Vice Chairman and Trustee, Wolf Trap Foundation for the Performing Arts; Trustee, United States Supreme Court Historical Society; Board Member, Development Council at the University of Michigan; and member, Committee of Visitors of the University of Michigan Law School.
Taylor belonged to a number of clubs, including the University Club (New York), George Town Club (Washington), and Lyford Cay Club (Nassau, Bahamas). He received honorary degrees from the Agricultural Technical College of North Carolina, Pacific University, Sham University, and Knoxville College. Among his numerous awards and commendations, the following may be cited: Achievement Award, National Business League (1964); Distinguished Service Award, U.S. Department of Labor (1964); Commandeur de l'Ordre National de la Republique de Cote D'Ivoire (1969); University of Michigan Sesquicentennial Award (1972); Distinguished Public Service Award, U.S. Navy (1974); and the NAACP Award for Distinguished Service (1975).
Hobart Taylor died on April 2, 1981.
The Hobart Taylor, Jr. papers document his work in various staff positions in the Kennedy and Johnson administrations, Democratic Party activities and his service on several government committees and work with business and civic organizations relating to civil rights, equal employment opportunities and economic development. The papers have been organized into the following ten series: Personal, Correspondence, President's Committee on Equal Employment Opportunities, Plans for Progress, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, Commandant of the Marine Corps' Advisory Committee on Minority Affairs, Export-Import Bank, Topical files, Awards, and Photographs.
Subjects:
African Americans.; Banks and banking--United States.; Civil rights--United States.; Democratic Party (U.S.); Discrimination in employment--United States.; Export-Import Bank of Washington.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; Oral history.; Plans for Progress.; United States Marine Corps' Commandant's Advisory Committee for Minority Affairs.; United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.; United States. President's Committee on Equal Employment Opportunity.
Subjects - Visual Material:
African Americans.; Bentley Historical Library.; Export-Import Bank of Washington.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Hunt, Richard, 1935-; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Outdoor sculpture--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Plans for Progress.; Sculpture.; United States. President's Committee on Equal Employment Opportunity.; University of Michigan--Students--1941-1950.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series consists of biographical data, newspaper clippings, and printed material about Hobart Taylor. Taylor's addresses, speeches and remarks are also contained in this personal series; they are arranged chronologically from 1961-1980. There are also three oral history interviews in which Taylor discusses his political work, his contributions to the President's Committee on Equal Employment Opportunities and Plans for Progress, and his contributions to the civil rights movement.
  - Biographical Data, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Congratulations upon appointment as White House Counsel 1964 (Box 1)
  - Congratulations upon appointment to Realty Board 1968 (Box 1)
  - Oral History Interview
    - John F. Kennedy Library 1967 (Box 1)
    - The University of Texas 1969 (Box 1)
    - Middleburg, Virginia 1977 (Box 1)
  - Christmas Cards sent by Taylor (Box 1)
  - Letters to the Editor
    - Newsweek, June 29, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Fortune Magazine, May 18, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - re. Hobart Taylor, Jr., 6 folders (Box 1)
    - re. Hobart Taylor, Sr (Box 1)
    - re. Lynette Taylor (Box 1)
  - Statement by Taylor re. Muskie's remark on possibility of a Black Vice-President (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Printed materials re. Hobart Taylor, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Addresses, Speeches, Remarks
    - Undated, 1961-1970, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - 1971-1980, 8 folders (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series is arranged chronologically, and then alphabetically within each year. Correspondence includes both in-coming and out-going letters and deals with personal matters, political and government work, business affairs, and organizations in which Taylor held membership.
  - 1961-1964
    - A-Z, 28 folders (Box 2)
  - 1965
    - A-Z, 28 folders (Box 3)
  - 1966
    - A-D, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - E-Z, 16 folders (Box 4)
  - 1967-1968
    - A-V, 22 folders (Box 4)
    - W-Z, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 1969
    - A-Z, 17 folders (Box 5)
    - January-June (Box 5)
    - July-Dec (Box 5)
  - 1970
    - A-Z, 16 folders (Box 5)
    - January-June (Box 5)
    - July-Dec (Box 5)
  - 1971-1972
    - A-Z, 18 folders (Box 5)
    - January-June 1971 (Box 5)
    - July-December 1971 (Box 5)
    - January-June 1972 (Box 5)
    - July-December 1972 (Box 5)
  - 1973
    - A-Z, 16 folders (Box 6)
    - January-June 1973 (Box 6)
    - July-December 1973 (Box 6)
  - 1974-1975
    - A-Z, 16 folders (Box 6)
    - January-June 1974 (Box 6)
    - July-December 1974 (Box 6)
  - 1976-1979
    - A-G, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - H-Z, 8 folders (Box 7)
  - 1980
    - January-June 1980 (Box 7)
    - July-December 1980 (Box 7)
  - 1981
    - January-December 1981 (Box 7)
- President's Committee On Equal Employment Opportunity
  Included in this series are memoranda and correspondence covering the years 1962 to 1965, minutes of meetings, and some material on the President's Committee on Equal Opportunity in Housing and the new Equal Opportunity Commission.
  - Correspondence 1962-1965, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Memoranda 1963-1965, 7 folders (Box 7)
  - Investigation re. Leaks to Press 1962 (Box 7)
  - Budget Figures (Box 7)
  - Crown-Zellerback Corporation (Box 7)
  - Government Survey on the Utilization of Minority Personnel 1962 (Box 7)
  - Labor Advisory Council
    - March 15, 1963 (Box 7)
    - April 23, 1964 (Box 7)
    - May 12, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Report to the President November 26, 1963 (Box 7)
  - President's Committee on Equal Opportunity in Housing (Box 7)
  - New Equal Opportunity Commission (Box 8)
  - Printed Materials (Box 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Press Releases (Box 8)
- Plans for Progress
  The series, Plans for Progress, has been divided into five subseries. The first subseries is Administrative Records and consists of memoranda, committee reports, budget and personnel materials, and summaries of activities and accomplishments. The second is Topical and includes files on the Advertising Council, the Advisory Committee, the Association of Huntsville Area Contractors, the Department of Labor, Federally-assisted Training Programs, Local Merit Employment Councils, and the On-the-Job Training Program. The third subseries contains material on various conferences and meetings held by Plans for Progress, and the fourth includes speeches, publications and newspaper clippings relating to Plans for Progress. The final subseries is composed of two files of miscellaneous material.
  - Administrative Records
    - Incorporation, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - General Correspondence and Memoranda (Box 8)
    - Summary of Activities and Accomplishments 1965-1968 (Box 8)
    - Reports, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Research (Box 8)
    - Steering Committee (Box 8)
    - Staff Members (Box 8)
    - Administrative Director (Box 8)
    - Administrative Coordinator (Box 8)
    - Budget and Personnel, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Wirtz, Willard (Sec. of Labor)
      - Correspondence and Memoranda (Box 8)
    - Humphrey, Hubert (Vice-President)
      - Correspondence and Memoranda 1964-1968, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Weekly Reports (Box 8)
    - Task Force on Youth Motivation
      - General (Box 8)
      - February 11, 1966 Meeting (Box 9)
      - June 14, 1966 Meeting (Box 9)
    - Vice-President's Letter of October 27, 1967 (Box 9)
    - Speeches and Remarks (Box 9)
  - Topical File
    - Advertising Council, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Advisory Council
      - General, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Chairman (Box 9)
      - Committees
        - General (Box 9)
        - Committee on Housing (Box 9)
      - Meetings
        - General (Box 9)
        - January 14, 1966 (Box 9)
        - March 18, 1966 (Box 9)
        - May 26, 1966 (Box 9)
        - October 20, 1966 (Box 9)
        - December 8, 1966 (Box 9)
        - April 14, 1967 (Box 9)
        - September 7, 1967 (Box 9)
        - March 19, 1969 (Box 9)
        - May 5, 1969 (Box 9)
        - September 26, 1969 (Box 9)
        - News Letter (Box 9)
    - Archbishop's Committee on Civil Rights (Box 9)
    - Association of Huntsville Area Contractors
      - Memoranda and Correspondence 1964-1969, 4 folders (Box 9)
      - Minutes (Box 9)
      - Reports (Box 9)
      - Printed Materials (Box 9)
    - Civil Rights Act (Box 9)
    - Connecticut Council For Equal Employment Opportunity (Box 9)
    - Department of Labor
      - Office of Federal Contract Compliance (Box 9)
      - News Digest (Box 9)
    - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (Box 10)
    - Federally Assisted Training Programs
      - General (Box 10)
      - Manpower Development Seminars (Box 10)
    - Ford Foundation (Box 10)
    - Job Opportunity Training, Inc (Box 10)
    - Letter of May 11, 1964 (Box 10)
    - Local Merit Employment Councils
      - General (Box 10)
      - Cleveland, Ohio (Box 10)
      - Milwaukee, Wisconsin (Box 10)
    - National Alliance of Businessmen (Box 10)
    - New Orleans Voluntary Equal Employment Opportunity Council
      - On-the-Job Training Program (Box 10)
      - General (Box 10)
    - Promotion and Development Program (Box 10)
    - Philadelphia Plan (Box 10)
    - President's Committee on Equal Employment Opportunity (Box 10)
    - Race Relations Center (Box 10)
    - Southern Regional Council (Box 10)
    - Summer Employment Task Force (Box 10)
    - Vocational Guidance Institutes (Box 10)
  - Conferences and Meetings
    - General, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Anniversary Conference June 6, 1966 (Box 10)
    - Bankers Introductory Meeting May 23, 1967 (Box 10)
    - Business Executives Conference April 28, 1965 (Box 10)
    - College Relations Conference
      - November 2-4, 1965 (Box 10)
      - December 12-14, 1966 (Box 10)
    - Dinner Meetings 1965-1968 (Box 10)
    - National Conferences
      - Third Annual January 25-26, 1965 (Box 10)
      - Fourth Annual January 24-25, 1966 (Box 10)
      - Fifth Annual January 23-24, 1967 (Box 10)
      - Sixth Annual January 22-23, 1968 (Box 10)
    - Northwest Regional Conference June 10, 1965 (Box 10)
    - President's Luncheon July 5, 1967 (Box 10)
    - Recruitment Meetings October 3, 1967 (Box 10)
    - Regional Conference (New Orleans) November 10, 1966 (Box 10)
    - Reunion Dinner November 19, 1980 (Box 10)
    - White House Conference ("To Fulfill These Rights") June 1-2, 1966, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - White House Meetings (Box 11)
  - Speeches, Publications, Newspaper Clippings
    - Speech Materials (Box 11)
    - Speeches (Box 11)
    - General Publications (Box 11)
    - Corporate Publications (Box 11)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 11)
- National Association For The Advancement Of Colored People
  The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People series consists of correspondence from 1975 to 1980 and a topical subseries. Materials relating to the Committee on Inquiry and the Special Contribution Fund are especially plentiful.
  - General Correspondence
    - 1975-1980, 6 folders (Box 11)
  - Topical File
    - Annual Board Meeting January 1980 (Box 11)
    - Award for Distinguished Service April 23, 1975 (Box 11)
    - Bakke-Affirmative Action Statement (Box 11)
    - Bell, Griffin (U.S. Attorney-General) (Box 11)
    - Bryce, Herrington (Box 11)
    - Business Advisory Committee, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Cobb, Montague (Box 11)
    - Committee of Four to Meet with Robert Strauss (Box 12)
    - Committee on Discrimination in the Media (Box 12)
    - Committee on Election of National Officers (Box 12)
    - Committee on Inquiry, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Committee on Policy and Plans 1977-1980, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - Crisis Magazine (Box 12)
    - Economic Policy Advisory Council, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Energy Statements (Box 12)
    - Hooks, Benjamin (Box 12)
    - Humphries, Derrick A. (Box 12)
    - Legal Defense Fund (Box 12)
    - National Steering Committee (Box 12)
    - Pension Survey Committee Report (Box 12)
    - Personnel Committee (Box 12)
    - Search and Screening Committee (Box 12)
    - Special Contributions Fund Correspondence 1966-1970, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Special Contributions Fund Correspondence 1971-1972, 8 folders (Box 13)
    - Task Force on Africa (Box 13)
    - Testimony Before the House Subcommittee on Employment Opportunities June 26, 1979 (Box 13)
    - Wilkins, Roy (Box 13)
    - Wilson, Margaret Bush, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Yeager, James H (Box 13)
- Commandant of the Marine Corps' Advisory Committee for Minority Affairs
  The series, the Commandant of the Marine Corps' Advisory Committee for Minority Affairs is organized into the following five subseries: Correspondence (1970-1979), Minutes, Reports, Fact Book (1971), and Miscellaneous. Minutes of meetings are limited mainly to the period 1971-1973. Reports include information about a number of investigative trips, for example to Camp Pendleton (1972, 1974) and to Okinawa (1970, 1972, 1975).
  - Correspondence 1970-1974, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - Correspondence 1975-1979, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Minutes
    - October 8, 1971 (Box 14)
    - November 12, 1971 (Box 14)
    - June 1-2, 1972 (Box 14)
    - September 14, 1973 (Box 14)
  - Reports
    - Camp Pendleton Trip
      - 1972, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - 1974 (Box 14)
    - Determination To Hold Closed Meetings 1973 (Box 14)
    - Leadership/Human Relations Program 1975 (Box 14)
    - Military Justice 1972 (Box 14)
    - Minority Enlistment 1973 (Box 14)
    - Okinawa Trip
      - 1970 (Box 14)
      - 1972 (Box 14)
      - 1975 (Box 14)
    - Parris Island Trip 1976 (Box 14)
    - Race Relations/Human Affairs (First Marine Division) 1971 (Box 14)
    - San Diego Trip 1977 (Box 14)
  - Fact Book 1971, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 15)
- Export-Import Bank
  The Export-Import Bank series relates to Taylor's work as a Director bank and include correspondence (1965-1968), agenda sheets, and material from Taylor's Asian trip in 1966 and from his African trip in 1967. Of particular interest is an analysis of the automobile market in Thailand.
  - General Correspondence 1965-1968, 1975, 5 folders (Box 15)
  - Agenda Sheets
    - Formal Board Meetings (Box 15)
    - Informal Board Meetings (Box 15)
  - African Trip 1966
    - Correspondence (Box 15)
    - Briefing Book (Box 15)
    - Final Report (Box 15)
  - Asian Trip 1967 (Box 15)
  - Automobile Market in Thailand (Box 15)
  - Holland and England Trip 1966 (Box 15)
  - Webb-Pomerene Act (Box 15)
- Topical File
  Topical Files contain materials relating to Taylor's memberships in various organizations, his charitable and civic activities, his business dealings and government service. Included in the files is valuable information about national politics in the 1960's (e.g. files on Lyndon Johnson, the Democratic Party, Hubert Humphrey, White House Staff, Texas politics, and Taylor's political observations). Other major topics included in this series are the following: A Better Chance, Inc.; American Red Cross; A & P; Inaugural Committee (1965); Eliot Janeway Ling-Temco-Vought, Inc.; Motown; National Merit Scholarship Corporation; Proctor and Gamble Co.; Pullman Incorporated; University of Michigan; Wolf Trap Foundation for the Performing Arts; Zieger Osteopathic Hospital (Detroit).
  - A Better Chance, Inc. Correspondence 1969-1974, 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Civil Rights (Box 15)
  - Advertising Council (Box 15)
  - Aetna Fund, Inc (Box 16)
  - American Arbitration Association (Box 16)
  - American Association of Blacks In Energy (Box 16)
  - American Festival of Music (Box 16)
  - American Hospital Supply Corporation (Box 16)
  - American National Red Cross
    - Correspondence 1970-1977, 7 folders (Box 16)
    - United Givers Fund Task Force (Box 16)
  - Asia Society (Box 16)
  - Associated Land Interests and Development Corporation (Box 16)
  - Association for the Study of Negro Life and History, Inc (Box 16)
  - Association of American Railroads (Box 16)
  - Blacks In Management (Box 16)
  - Blake Construction Company (Box 16)
  - Board of Trade (Box 16)
  - Boggs, Congresswoman Lindy (Box 16)
  - Boulevard General Hospital (Box 16)
  - Brimberg and Company (Box 16)
  - Brown, Mrs. Ben (Barbara) (Box 16)
  - Browne, Elizabeth and John (Box 16)
  - Cahalan, William L (Box 16)
  - Cesaro v. Juusela (litigation) (Box 16)
  - Chennault, Benjamin (Box 16)
  - Chrysler Corporation Correspondence 1967-1974, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Citizens Small Business Investment Corporation (Box 16)
  - City and Country School of Bloomfield Hills, Michigan (Box 16)
  - Civil Rights Act 1964 (Box 16)
  - Civil Service Commission (Box 16)
  - Commission on Postal Service (Box 16)
  - Community Relations Service (Box 16)
  - Conference Board (Box 16)
  - Congressional Black Caucus (Box 16)
  - Connally, John (Box 16)
  - Connecticut General Life Insurance Co
    - Correspondence 1969 (Box 16)
    - Signed Contracts, Documents, etc (Box 16)
    - Interoffice Memos and Drafts (Box 16)
  - Council on Foreign Relations (Box 16)
  - Council on International Law and Foreign Trade (Box 16)
  - Crescent Park Company (Box 16)
  - Cutler-Hammer, Inc (Box 16)
  - Dacor and Dacor House (Box 17)
  - Del Rio, James (Box 17)
  - Delta Oil Limited (Nigeria) (Box 17)
  - Democratic National Committee (Box 17)
  - Democratic National Convention (Box 17)
  - Democratic Party (Box 17)